<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elements>
<info>
  <name>Oath of the Raven</name>
  <update version="2.1">
    <file 
      name="paladin-raven.xml"
      url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/VerathragnaEA/aurora/main/paladin-raven.xml" />
  </update>
</info>

<!-- ARCHETYPE -->
<element name="Oath of the Raven" type="Archetype" source="Homebrew: Oath of the Raven" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN">
  <supports>Sacred Oath</supports>
  <description>
    <p>Paladins of the Oath of the Raven dedicate their souls to the service of the Raven Queen. These knights honor the beauty of life and the sanctity of death, and swear to destroy anything that disrupts the natural cycle. Known as Knights of the Raven, they serve as the Raven Queen’s emissaries in the mortal realm.</p>

    <h5 class="caption">Tenets of the Raven</h5>
    <p>The Oath of the Raven demands reverence for death as an impartial certainty, and for the passage beyond the veil as a necessity.</p>

    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Let the End Come.</em></strong> All lives move toward their final moment. Do not hasten it, do not delay it.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Guard the Passage.</em></strong> The dead must pass beyond the veil. Suffer no force that binds a soul against its time.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Preserve the Cycle.</em></strong> Those who fracture the cycle of life and death must be stopped.</p>
    <p class="indent"><strong><em>Stand Beyond Judgment.</em></strong> Do not weigh the soul or pass sentence. You are not the arbiter—only the still hand.</p>

    <div element="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_OATH_SPELLS" />
    <div element="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_CHANNEL_DIVINITY" />
    <div element="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_AURA_OF_SHADOWS" />
    <div element="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_KNIGHT_OF_RETRIBUTION" />
    <div element="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_RAVEN_QUEENS_CHAMPION" />
  </description>
  <sheet display="false" />
  <rules>
    <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_OATH_SPELLS" level="3" />
    <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_CHANNEL_DIVINITY" level="3" />
    <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_AURA_OF_SHADOWS" level="7" />
    <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_KNIGHT_OF_RETRIBUTION" level="15" />
    <grant type="Archetype Feature" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_RAVEN_QUEENS_CHAMPION" level="20" />
  </rules>
</element>

<!-- CHANNEL DIVINITY -->
<element name="Channel Divinity: Chains of Shadow" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Oath of the Raven" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_CHANNEL_DIVINITY_CHAINS_OF_THE_DARK_FEATHER">
  <sheet action="Action" usage="Channel Divinity">
    <description>
      As an action, chains of living darkness rise from the shadows beneath creatures of your choice within 30 feet.
      Each target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or have its speed reduced to 0 for {{pb:turns}} turns.
      If the target is an undead or a fiend, it is also restrained and has disadvantage on attack rolls.
      Affected creatures can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of their turns, ending the effect on a success.
    </description>
  </sheet>
  <rules>
    <stat name="pb:turns" value="proficiencybonus" />
  </rules>
</element>

<!-- 15th LEVEL -->
<element name="Marked by the Queen" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Oath of the Raven" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_KNIGHT_OF_RETRIBUTION">
  <description>
    <p><em>15th-level Oath of the Raven feature</em></p>
    <p>Whenever a creature hits you with an attack, it is marked until the end of your next turn. While marked, it has disadvantage on saving throws against effects you create. Whenever you deal damage to it, it takes extra necrotic damage equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum 1). Undead and fiends take double this damage and cannot regain hit points while marked.</p>
  </description>
  <sheet>
    <description>
      When a creature hits you with an attack, it is marked. When you deal damage to it, it takes {{mark:cha}} necrotic damage
      ({{mark:cha}} × 2 against undead or fiends) and cannot regain hit points.
    </description>
  </sheet>
  <rules>
    <stat name="mark:cha" value="charisma:modifier" />
  </rules>
</element>

<!-- 20th LEVEL -->
<element name="Avatar of the Raven Queen" type="Archetype Feature" source="Homebrew: Oath of the Raven" id="ID_HOME_OATH_OF_THE_RAVEN_RAVEN_QUEENS_CHAMPION">
  <description>
    <p><em>20th-level Oath of the Raven feature</em></p>
    <p>As an action, you become the Avatar of the Raven Queen for 1 minute. Shadow gathers around you, and vast raven wings of living darkness unfurl from your form. You gain silent flight (60 ft., hover), immunity to fear and charm, automatic success against forced movement, and whenever you deal damage directly to a creature, that damage ignores resistance and treats immunity as resistance.</p>
    <p>Once you use this feature, you can’t use it again until you finish a long rest.</p>
  </description>
  <sheet action="Action" usage="1/Long Rest">
    <description>
      Become the Avatar of the Raven Queen for 1 minute. Gain silent flight, immunity to fear and charm,
      immunity to forced movement, and ignore resistance (treat immunity as resistance) on damage you deal directly.
    </description>
  </sheet>
</element>

</elements>
